Guide to the Henry S. Churchill papers, 1929-1962
Churchill, Henry S. papers, 1929-1962
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry S. Churchill papers, 1929-1962
2347
Henry S. Churchill
4.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, speeches, reports, course material, a manuscript inventory, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, speeches, course material, and other papers relating to Henry S. Churchill's career as an architect and city planner.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry S. Churchill was an architect and city planner.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence pertains to the National Competitions Committee for Architecture and Allied Arts, the Federación Panamericana de Asociaciones de Arquitectos, competitions of the Union Internationale des Architectes, the 1958 U.I.A. Congress at Moscow, the establishment of a closer relationship between the U.I.A. and United Nations groups concerned with housing and urban development, especially UNESCO, other U.I.A. business and the teaching and practice of city planning; the Eastwick (Philadelphia) Redevelopment Project; and Churchill's proposed book on the architect Eugène Emmanuel Viollet-le-Duc. Correspondents include Samuel Inman Cooper, Frederick H. Dechant, William Gehron, Jane Jacobs, Marc Peter, Jr., Lorimer Rich, Walter A. Taylor, Pierre Vago, Wolf von Eckhardt, Ralph Walker, Ernest Weissman, the American Institute of Architects, the American Institute of Planners, and the Redevelopment Authority of Philadelphia. Manuscript notes for "A Study of Architecture"; manuscript copies of speeches; a manuscript inventory (1 vol.) of Churchill's architectural library; and reports (typescript carbon copies, 1942-1944) made by Churchill and Albert Mayer to the Director of Defense Housing on housing projects in North and South Carolina, Connecticut, Maryland, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, and Virginia.
Also, notes and printed material pertaining to courses taught by Churchill at Columbia University, redevelopment in the Germantown, East Falls, Eastwick, and Roxborough sections of Philadelphia; and printed reports and related items concerning planning projects in San Francisco, California; New Haven, Connecticut; Gainesville and Orlando, Florida; the Greenbelt towns; Forest Park, Illinois; Hoboken, Jersey City, and Radburn, New Jersey; Garden City and Long Island City, New York; Sewickley Borough, Pennsylvania; Talara, Peru; and at the University of Florida and George Washington University. In addition, reports, minutes, agenda, newsletters, releases, notices, and printed matter pertaining to the activities of the U.I.A., A.I.A., A.I.P., housing committees of the U.N., and the Philadelphia Citizens' Council on City Planning.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Churchill, Henry S. (Henry Stern); Cooper, Samuel Inman.; Dechant, Frederick.; Jacobs, Jane, 1916-; Mayer, Albert, b. 1897.; Peter, Marc, Jr.; Rich, Lorimer.; Taylor, Walter A.; Vago, Pierre, 1910-; Viollet-le-Duc, Eugène-Emmanuel, 1814-1879.; Von Eckhardt, Wolf.; Walker, Ralph, 1889-1973.; Weissman, Ernest.; American Institute of Architects.; American Institute of Planners.; Columbia University--Planning.; Federación Panamericana de Asociaciones de Arquitectos.; George Washington University--Planning.; International Union of Architects.; National Competitions Committee for Architecture and Allied Arts.; Philadelphia Citizens' Council on City Planning.; Philadelphia (Pa.). Redevelopment Authority.; Unesco.; United Nations.; University of Florida.
Subjects:
Architecture.; City planning.; Housing--Effect of wars on.; Housing--Connecticut.; Housing--Maryland.; Housing--New Jersey.; Housing--New York.; Housing--North Carolina.; Housing--Pennsylvania.; Housing--South Carolina.; Housing--Virginia.; City planners.
Places:
City planning--Illinois--Forest Park.; City planning--Florida--Gainesville.; City planning--New York (State)--Garden City.; City planning--New Jersey--Hoboken.; City planning--New Jersey--Jersey City.; City planning--New York (State)--Long Island City.; City planning--Connecticut--New Haven.; City planning--Florida--Orlando.; City planning--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; City planning--New Jersey--Radburn.; City planning--California--San Francisco.; City planning--Pennsylvania--Sewickley.; City planning--Peru--Talara.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- File: 24, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Union Internationales des Architectes (UIA), 1943-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- UIA, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
- n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Lectures ("File 24"), 1938-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Lectures, talks, etc., 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Lectures, talks, etc., 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Lectures, talks, etc., 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Lectures, talks, etc., 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Lectures, talks, etc., 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Notes for A Study of Architecture: Symbols of Abstractions which Man, ... (Box 1, Folder 23-26)
- Aspects of City Design - rough notes (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Symposium: Urban renewal: Cleveland, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Architectural library of Henry S. Churchill, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Engagement books, 1949-1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Address book (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Housing and urban planning, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Study of dwelling shelter and congestion, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Study of patterns of urban congestion, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Patterns of congestion, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Conference with U.S.I.A. regarding Moscow Exhibit, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Planning draft, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Historical research - A.I.A. Committee on Housing (Box 1, Folder 38)
- The dwelling in Greater Manhattan, 1850-1950 - Part II: The Apartment, 1850-1890, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
- A.I.A. NEWS, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Planning the home for occupancy, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Construction and Equipment of the Home, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- A Planning Study of the Tarrytowns, Colombia University, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- A Planning Study of the Village of Dobbs Ferry, Colombia, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- A development program for the Fourth Ward Area of Passaic (NJ), Colombia, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Projects visited, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Greenbelt Towns manuscript (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Greenbelt Towns manuscript - appendices (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Greenbrook, NJ - Greendale, Wis. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Greenbrook, NJ, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Greenbrook, NJ project book (Box 2, Folder 11-24)
- National Association of Housing & Redevelopment Officials - International Committee, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- National Competitions Committee for Architecture and the Allies Arts, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Report: "Densities in New York City", 1944 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Report: "Excerpts from the Comprehensive Plan - The Physical Development Plan for the City of Philadelphia", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Reports - Citizen's Council on City Planning, 1950-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "Housing for the Aged", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "The Philadelphia Housing Association", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- "The Attack on Town Planning: A Reply to Opponents of the Suburban Resettlement Towns" (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Union Internationales des Architectes (UIA), 1950-1961 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
- UIA, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- UIA, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- UIA, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
- Talara, Peru - International Petroleum Co., Ltd., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Architectural Advisory Panel - Evaluation Report, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Elm Haven Housing Project, New Haven Ct. (file #32) (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Report on the Development Plan for the George Washington University, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- District of Colombia Redevelopment Land Agency contract, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Gainesville, Florida, Planning Board of, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Report of a Study of Traffic and Parking at the University of Florida, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- University of Florida, Gainesville, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Master Guide Plan for Gainesville, Florida, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Comprehensive City Planning Report - Orlando, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Economic and Housing Survey of the Orlando Metro-Region, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Report on the Community Facilities of Park Forest, Illinois, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- City of Hoboken, New Jersey - Major Streets and regulation of traffic, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Jersey City, New Jersey Preliminary Planning Survey, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- A summary of the finances of Jersey City, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Jersey City, New Jersey - Report to the Planning Board, Vol 1, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Jersey City, New Jersey - Report to the Planning Board, Vol 2, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- A development program for the Fourth Ward Area of Passaic, New Jersey, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Radburn Protective Restrictions and Community Administration, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Garden City, New York Board of Zoning appeals (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Queensbridge Housing Project (NY), 1933 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Queensbridge Housing Project (NY) summary report, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Queensbridge Housing Project (NY) supplementary report, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Queensbridge Housing Project (NY) plans and studies (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Sewickly (Pa.) District Plan, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Housing and Social Structure: A preliminary survey (Philadelphia Housing Authority), 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Summary report on the Central Urban Renewal Area (CURA), Philadelphia, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
- Norwalk, Ct. - subdivision regulations, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Industrial Land and Facilities for Philadelphia, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
- Center City, Philadelphia, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Philadelphia - East Falls, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
- Philadelphia - Lower Eastwick Area, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Philadelphia - Upper Eastwick, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Philadelphia - Eastwick District, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Philadelphia - Eastwick Area, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Philadelphia - Eastwick Area, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Philadelphia - Eastwick Area, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
- Report on the Redevelopment of Eastwick, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Eastwick: part of agreement - planning and engineering, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Eastwick - Mingo Creek, Lagoon, and Pumping Station, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Eastwick - Phase I Report, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Eastwick Project minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Study of a Portion of Germantown, Pa, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Germantown Leadership Area, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Germantown - A Planning Study, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Germantown note cards (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Concern for Germantown (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Germantown (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Germantown, First Presbyterian Church Study, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Germantown School District, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Germantown (?) industry and employment (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Germantown zoning map changes, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Germantown Commission on Human Relations (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Germantown (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Philadelphia City Planning Commission and Philadelphia Housing Authority (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Philadelphia City Planning Commission redevelopment areas (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Preliminary Study of Germantown, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Concern for Germantown, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- A Proposal for the Revitalization of the Heart of Germantown (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Germantown Settlement - minutes, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Germantown (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Report on Roxborough Area, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Mount Vernon (file#32) (NY?), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Densities in New York City, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Eastwick Renewal Area, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Easwick Job #302, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Zoning Study (Box 4, Folder 25)
- For Columbia University Seminar "The Social Implications...", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Specifications for North Country Day School, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Haskell Diary (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Stein Analysis Whittlesey - application to Bound Brook (Box 4, Folder 29)
- "Notes on a French Horn" and other notes (not used) (Box 4, Folder 30)
- "Notes on a French Horn" prime copy (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Articles by Churchill (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Mexican Delegation of Architects and City Planners proposal, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- New York Chapter, AIA - "Patrons of Congestion", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Atlantic City, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Sale of Harrison House (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Report of the Committee on Honorary Fellows - AIA, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Churchill House - backed up specs for printing, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- House - contract, change orders, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Weissman House, Job no. 300, outline specs - "Heating", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Weissman House, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Committee on Committees, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Dwelling unit figures (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Riverside - A study of Housing on the West Side of Manhattan - AIA, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
- Articles, reprints, various papers (Box 4, Folder 46)